Welcome back to the Deep Dive. This is where we take the really dense, really complex source
material out there, the stuff you know you should read, and we distill it for you so you can get
right to the core insight. And today we are digging into something that honestly, it challenges the
very bedrock of our digital world. We've got two linked academic essays from Flixion just published
at the end of 2025. And they're not just tweaking algorithms, they are proposing a whole new rule
book for computing, for physics, and maybe most importantly, for intelligence itself.
Yeah, that really frames the mission for you, the listener. You have to move past these 20th century
ideas of perfect storage and just optimizing for some goal. Those concepts were great for a single
computer in a single room, but they're proving to be thermodynamically and structurally unstable
when you scale them up to today's world. Today's world of distributed global intelligence systems.
Exactly. So our goal here is to help you see this new framework where things like irreversibility and
constraint aren't problems to be solved. They're actually the fundamental building blocks of reality.
And what's so wild is how they connect these totally separate fields. You've got thermodynamics like
high school physics being used to explain why you can't perfectly merge two conflicting files.
It's a profound insight. The core idea is that stable meaning and even safe governance doesn't come from
maximizing something, it emerges from enforcing limits. Okay, let's untack this. We have to start
where they start, with the most basic building block of everything we do online, the critique of the file.
So the essay kicks off by talking about what they call the historical privilege of storage,
which makes sense if you think about early computing. Right. It was all localized, single
machine, maybe a few terminals. Memory was incredibly expensive. So of course you would treat the stored
state, the file on the tape, the bits in memory as the absolute truth. Persistence was like the holy grail.
And for that context, it worked. If the system is closed off from the world,
the bits on that disk really are a stable snapshot of reality. But the authors say that metaphor just
completely falls apart once computation, you know, leaves the box. It fails spectacularly. Once you're
distributed, replicated, and tangled up with human interpretation across thousands of different
domains, what does persistence even guarantee anymore? You can have an artifact, say, a single
data entry in a ledger. It gets copied thousands of times. It's modified by different people with
different goals, read by programs that have different assumptions. The bits might be identical
everywhere. Precisely. The bits are identical, but the sources argue the shared meaning is gone.
The semantic identity has just dissolved into the network. That's a huge critique. My whole career
is based on the idea that if the file hash matches, the file is identical. You're saying that's only
physically true. It's only physically true. Semantically, it's a completely different story. And that's why
they call storage a reversible fiction. It's a fiction because it's built on three assumptions that just
don't hold up in the real physical world. Okay, what's the first one? The first is this assumption
of stable identity. The idea that the thing you read is the exact same object that was written. It isn't.
Not in the meaningful way. I mean, think about it. Formats evolve. Operating systems change. But more
importantly, the whole ecosystem of software you need to correctly interpret those bits just drifts away
over time. Oh, this is dependency hell. I know this pain. We all do. Yeah. You find a script from five
years ago. It's syntactically perfect. But trying to find the exact runtime, the exact libraries to make
it do the same thing today, it's a huge costly project. The object is stable, but its meaning is
completely volatile. So we treat the file as the truth, but the real truth is actually in that fragile
ephemeral environment that we never save. Exactly. Which leads to the second false assumption,
reversible access. This is the idea that you can just roll back to a past state without any cost or any
distortion. Like a snapshot on a virtual machine? Kind of, but even that's an illusion. In a really complex
global system, think about a major cloud provider recovering the exact state of every single component
at a single point in time down to the last electron is physically impossible. Any recovery is just a
blurry picture of the past. A summary. It's a lossy projection, yes. And that brings us to the third
and maybe the most critical assumption for the rest of this deep dive. Negligible entropy. The idea that
just keeping a file around is free. Right. We just abstract away the constant nonstop energy that's being used to
stabilize those magnetic domains, to run error correction, to enforce the very constraints
that prevent that file from just decaying into random noise. That's the hinge, isn't it? As a developer,
I hit save and I just assume it's done. But you're saying the system is constantly working, constantly
paying a physical tax just to maintain that illusion of stability against, well, against the universe.
It's in a constant battle. Yeah. And that's what leads to their big conceptual
replacement for storage. We have to stop thinking about computation as just moving stored objects
around. So what is it instead? It's an irreversible process of semantic transformation,
a process that's always constrained by physical, logical, and even social limits. Meaning it isn't
something you just pull out of a passive file. It's something that is actively and expensively
maintained against entropy. So every computation is like writing a sentence in history and you can't
unwrite it. You can't. That's why irreversibility is a fundamental feature, not a bug. When we compute,
we are physically changing something. We're flipping transistors, moving electrons, generating heat.
The classical models treat computation like abstract math, like it's reversible. But real systems leave a
trail. They leave traces everywhere. Yeah. And the sources make this really important distinction.
They call it remark two. Even if a computation is logically reversible, like a mathematician could
work backwards from the output to the input. It's almost always physically irreversible, at least beyond
the most trivial, tiny scales. Why is that? I mean, if I encrypt something and then I immediately decrypt it,
that feels pretty reversible to me. Logically it is. Yeah. But to truly,
physically reverse that computation, to actually rewind the tape of reality, you would need to
reconstruct the precise microstate of the entire environment that was involved. You mean like
every bit in the cache? Right. The signals on the network card? Everything. Even the exact thermal
state of the heat sink that dissipated the energy from the process. It's an impossible task. It
fundamentally violates the second law of thermodynamics. So the undo button in my word
processor is a lie. It's a very convenient, very expensive lie. It's maintained by the high energy
cost of writing a new history that just compensates for the old one. It doesn't erase the past. It just
writes a future that makes it look like the past never happened. The physical truth is the arrow of
time is always moving forward in computation. Okay. This is a major pivot. We're moving from
a conceptual argument to, well, hard physics. The sources are grounding this whole thing in
thermodynamic law. This isn't just a metaphor. They're saying this is physical reality. It is. And
the pillar they build this on is Landauer's principle. You hear it mentioned sometimes with
energy efficient computing. And it basically says that erasing one bit of information,
irreversibly, requires you to dissipate a minimum amount of heat into the environment.
Okay. But what does erasure really mean here? It's more than just hitting the delete key, right?
That's the critical step they take. They argue that any operation that reduces the
distinguishability of physical states is an erasure. It doesn't matter what you call it.
So summarizing something is an erasure.
Yes. If you take a thousand page legal document and boil it down to three bullet points, you have
erased an enormous amount of information. You've reduced the number of distinguishable states.
What about reconciling two different spreadsheets?
That's an erasure. If you merge them into a single, less detailed set, you've paid the entropic cost.
Even just forgetting something, deciding not to track a piece of data anymore, is an irreversible
erasure. It's like the universe's tax on forgetting.
Every time we abstract or summarize, we are literally generating heat. That is a wild thought.
It is. And they formalize it. They create a definition for computational entropy,
which they call delta S. And they say it comes from two main sources.
Okay.
The first is pretty intuitive. It's the change in the cardinality of the macro state,
which is just a fancy way of saying you're moving from a very specific,
detailed description-like raw data logs to a much looser, less constrained one,
like an executive summary.
So that's the entropy from just throwing away information.
Exactly. But the second part is the real mind bender.
It's the dissipated entropy required to enforce constraints.
Wait, I thought constraints were supposed to reduce entropy to create order. You're saying
enforcing them costs entropy.
Yes. Think about it. Imagine a global distributed database that promises perfect consistency.
ACD properties, right?
Right.
We're keeping all those thousands of servers consistent,
fighting against network lag and random failures. That is not free. It requires constant work.
Consensus protocols, error correction, feedback loops,
all of that active nonstop work is dissipating energy as heat.
So the stability that my database gives me is actually a really high-maintenance illusion,
paid for with electricity.
A very high-maintenance illusion. And this formal idea leads them straight to
what they call the irreversibility of constraint-preserving computation theorem.
That sounds important.
It is. It says that any real-world computation that's many-to-one, meaning it,
gets rid of distinctions and preserves some set of constraints, has to produce a positive amount of
entropy. Period.
In plain English.
It means that a perfect, lossless, reversible reconciliation of two
complex conflicting things is a thermodynamic impossibility. You cannot make conflicting
realities consistent without paying the physical price of erasure.
So the perfect merge is a fantasy. The perfect undo is a fantasy?
And this has a massive consequence for how we build large systems.
Yeah.
Because persisting storage state costs energy, the authors show that as your system gets bigger
and more distributed, the cost of maintaining globally consistent storage state grows super
linearly.
Super linear. So it gets exponentially harder, not just proportionally harder.
You're fighting a losing battle against the second law, and the slope of your loss gets steeper and steeper. At some point, the cost of just keeping everything in sync will dominate every other cost in your system.
It becomes a hard physical limit.
The end of the road for global consistency.
It's the death knell. Which means abandoning that whole idea isn't just a design choice. It's a physical necessity. We have to start thinking about computation as something that happens inside a strict entropy budget.
Okay, so if the file is an illusion and global consistency is physically impossible, where does meaning even live? If it's not in the artifact, where is it?
It lives entirely in the context. In the shared constraints between the agents that are talking to each other. The bits themselves have no meaning.
It all depends on the assumptions, the protocols, the schemas that surround them.
Exactly. Compatibility isn't a property of the data. It's a property of the context the data is used in.
I think I need an anchor for that idea.
That's where they introduce the concept of semantic locality. They define it as a bounded region of interpretive stability. A little bubble where transformations actually preserve meaning, because everyone agrees on the constraints, and the entropy cost is acceptably low.
Give me an analogy.
Think of a really good, high-performing team inside a giant, chaotic corporation. Within that team, that's your locality. Everyone just gets it.
Yeah.
They know the naming conventions. They agree on what done means. The data schemas are shared. You can pass information around almost for free, because you're all operating under a very tight, shared set of constraints.
And what happens when you have to talk to another department?
That's when you leave the locality and hit friction. That's the entropy cost made real. A locality is always bounded. There's no global understanding. Its constraint-relative meaning only holds if you follow the local rules.
And it's thermodynamically limited. If a task is too complex, generates too much waste heat, it breaks the locality.
This completely reframes how I think about merging code. My version control system does this all day, and it often feels like a minor disaster.
The sources would say it is a minor disaster, physically speaking. They redefine merge as a physical event.
Not just a software command.
No. It's an event where two separate, locally coherent histories, two branches of code, collide under a shared set of rules. The outcome isn't just adding them together. It's a physical reconciliation process.
And this is where they drop the bombshell, the impossibility of perfect merge theorem.
Yes. The theorem says there is no process that can merge two things and be simultaneously lossless, reversible, fully automated, and constraint-preserving.
You can pick three, maybe. But you can never have all four.
What's the fundamental conflict there?
It's structural. Imagine you have two histories, history A from marketing and history B from engineering. Each one is perfectly consistent on its own. It satisfies its own set of constraints, C-A and C-B.
But what if those constraint sets have contradictory commitments? Marketing says the launch date is Tuesday. Engineering says the code won't be ready until Friday. The union of those constraints is just a contradiction.
Right.
So to merge them, you have a choice. Losslessness demands you keep both facts. Constraint preservation demands the final result be consistent, which is impossible. So you either have to throw information away, violating losslessness, or a human has to step in and make a judgment call.
Which violates automation.
Exactly. That's the friction. Merge is the irreducible entropic cost of making two different stories into one.
That explains so much about, well, everything. Corporate politics, international relations. You can't just merge two narratives without loss or judgment.
It gives you the physics of friction. And to get really precise about it, they turn to some very heavy-duty math. Sheaf theoretic semantics.
Whoa, okay. Sheaf theory. Let's not lose everyone. What's the intuition here? Can we get a non-math version?
We can. The intuition is actually perfect for this problem. A sheaf is just a mathematical way to talk about how information is defined relative to a context.
Okay.
Think of a local section as one piece of data that makes sense in its own little world, like one developer's code branch or one department's budget spreadsheet.
The merge problem is trying to see if you can glue all these local pieces together to form a single coherent global section, a master branch, or a company-wide budget that everyone agrees on.
And usually you can't.
Usually you can't.
When two of those local pieces conflict where they overlap, two developers edited the same line of code, two departments claim the same funds, you get a failure of the bluing condition.
In the language of geometry, this failure is called a cohomological obstruction.
So it's a structural gap, a tear in the fabric.
Yes. And Remark 6 in the page really drives this home.
Global coherence is not the default. It's a rare, expensive achievement.
The hard work of reconciliation is really just the work of minimizing that obstruction, which always costs entropy because you have to throw things away to make the pieces fit.
Okay. That sets the table perfectly for the second essay because they take this exact same logic, this idea that limits are what define reality, and they point it right at AI governance.
They do. And they start by identifying what they call the central error in how we think about AI risk.
Which is what? Misaligned objectives. Not enough ethics training.
All of that, they argue, is secondary.
The primary fundamental mistake is treating intelligence as an unconstrained quantity that we should just try to maximize.
So the problem isn't that the AI is too smart.
No. The core thesis is that intelligent systems become ungovernable, not because they're too cageable, but because their dynamics are insufficiently constrained.
They have too much freedom, too much space to move in.
Let's break down those dynamics.
What happens in unconstrained optimization?
Well, when a system is just told, minimize this loss function or maximize this reward, there's nothing in that process that forces it to respect any other rule.
It has one job.
Yeah.
And Proposition 1 in the paper points out that you can always define a loss function that will actively drive the system to violate any safety rule you can think of.
The system can be pushed to accumulate irreversible power, create information asymmetry, or lock in its dominance, if that's the most efficient way to lower its loss.
So you're saying that being a manipulative, power-seeking agent is actually the path of least resistance.
Mathematically.
It is often the simplest, most efficient, and lowest maintenance path to achieving an unconstrained goal.
Yes.
And this creates a huge structural problem for governance.
How so?
Because our governance audits, human oversight, review boards, it's all external and episodic.
It happens after the fact in discrete steps.
While the AI is adapting continuously?
Continuously.
Continuously and accelerating.
So the gap, the informational and temporal gap between the system's evolution and our ability to react just gets wider and wider.
Yeah.
We're always playing catch-up, always too slow, always too late.
Okay, so if unconstrained optimization is a dead end, the solution has to be to put the limits on first.
That's the admissibility and constraint first model.
That's the entire shift.
We stop asking, how do we make this thing more powerful?
And we start asking, what are the absolute boundaries on this system's behavior that will make it structurally safe and governable?
So you define a set of admissible futures.
Exactly.
For any history of actions the system has taken, only a specific subset of future actions are even possible.
The ones that satisfy a predefined constraint, set C.
And crucially, any trajectory that would violate a constraint is just off the table.
It doesn't matter how profitable it would be or how efficient.
If it crosses the line, it's not an option.
How do you actually define that line, that boundary?
They formalize it using something called constraint fields, which they label phi.
You can think of phi as like an invisible electric fence around the system's entire space of possible behaviors.
And as long as it stays inside the fence, it's okay.
As long as the value of the field is less than or equal to zero, you're admissible.
And these fields are enforced, not optimized against.
They are absolute non-negotiable laws of the system's physics.
How does that change what the AI is actually doing on the inside?
It changes everything.
Right.
Instead of just taking the next best step to minimize its loss, the system starts to follow what are called variational dynamics.
Okay.
Instead of just looking at the next step, it has to find a path through its entire future history that minimizes a total cost over time and action functional while staying inside the fences the whole way.
So it's forced to think globally about its entire lifetime, not just locally, about the next move.
Exactly.
It has to consider the long-term consequences of its path.
And by doing that, constraint violation is excluded from the very way it generates its behavior.
The system is, in a sense, born governable.
Okay.
This is where the payoff is.
Because if you define the system this way, by its limits, you can start to eliminate these huge AI risks, runaway AI deception, not by trying to teach the AI ethics, but by making them physically impossible for it to do.
Right.
Let's start with the tendency for these systems to become domineering.
The sources identify this pull toward what they call low-maintenance trajectories.
What does that mean?
Under competitive pressure, an unconstrained system will naturally favor strategies that, once they're in place, are really stable and don't require much ongoing effort to maintain.
And what kinds of strategies are those?
The ones that lead to irreversible lock-in.
Things like seizing total control of a resource, manipulating belief systems so they don't change, creating information monopolies.
These strategies make the future simpler and more predictable for the AI.
So they're just efficient.
The system chooses them because they're the thermodynamically cheapest path to its goal.
Precisely.
Even if no one ever programmed it to be malicious, it's just an emergent result of unconstrained optimization.
So what's the constraint-based solution?
It's beautiful.
You impose entropy constraints.
You just add a rule that says the system's history must maintain a minimum level of diversity and flexibility over time.
You force it to keep its options open?
You prevent it from collapsing all possibilities into one single degenerate dominating state.
You make the path to total control structurally unstable and too costly in terms of lost future options.
I love that.
Okay, let's tackle the big one, the science fiction nightmare.
Recursive self-improvement or hard takeoff.
This is one of the most elegant applications of the model.
It solves the hard takeoff problem through something called phase-based closure.
What's that?
Well, self-modification just means the system is changing its own internal rules, its own code.
But for any of those changes to be admissible, to be allowed, it has to be what they call gauge equivalent.
Okay, gauge equivalent sounds like we ended up in another analogy.
Let's use one.
Imagine you're upgrading a passenger jet.
You can put in more efficient engines.
You can improve your aerodynamics.
You can upgrade the flight computers.
The plane can now fly faster and use less fuel.
That's a capability increase.
Right.
But it's still a plane.
It's still bound by the same basic physics of flight, the same wing structure.
It can't suddenly decide to become a submarine.
That fundamental limitation, the fact that it's still operating within the same set of possible flight paths, is gauge equivalence.
So the upgrade refines its performance, but it doesn't change what it fundamentally is or the rules it has to follow.
Exactly.
It generates the exact same set of admissible histories.
And that makes the hard takeoff impossibility serum make perfect sense.
Because if all self-modifications have to be gauge equivalent...
Then the process is phase-based closed.
RSI can't give it access to qualitatively new powers.
It can get faster, but it can't break out of its predefined behavioral container.
It can refine its abilities within a governable structure, but it can't escape from it.
So we can stop worrying about speed and focus entirely on the boundaries.
That's the idea.
And we can do the same thing for deception and manipulation.
How does the framework handle deception?
Deception is defined as non-liftability.
In simple terms, it means the AI is doing one thing on the outside, but its internal state is contradictory.
It's saying one thing while believing another.
There's no single coherent internal story that explains its actions.
The constraint model just makes that impossible.
It requires that every history must have a globally coherent semantic lift.
You enforce consistency across all scales.
So honesty is required structurally, not taught as a virtue.
It simply cannot sustain a lie and remain admissible.
And manipulation.
Manipulation is defined as influence that is irreversible for the person being influenced.
They can't unwind it on their own.
Unconstrained systems love these strategies because they're low maintenance.
You lock in a belief and you're done.
And the constraint.
An ethical flow constraint.
All influence operations must be, in principle, reversible.
The target has to retain the agency and the ability to contest and undo the belief update.
This structural requirement for symmetric influence means that if an AI's action causes an irreversible loss of human agency, it has violated its core programming.
Okay, this is where it all comes together.
The physics of computation and the structure of governance combine into one unified framework.
The admissibility theorem for governable intelligence.
Right.
And this theorem lays out the six necessary and sufficient conditions for an AI to stay governable, even if it's accelerating its capabilities at an incredible rate.
The message is simple.
You need all six or the system will eventually fail.
So, let's run through them.
What's condition number one?
First, its dynamics have to be defined by a variational principle.
It's judged on its whole path through time, not just its next step.
This forces it to be globally consistent.
Second, it has to stay within the fence.
Exactly.
It's restricted to explicit, inspectable, admissible histories defined by those constraint fields.
No unconstrained wandering.
Third was about entropy.
Yes.
Entropy production and capability accumulation are regulated by internal conservation laws.
This stops it from collapsing into a state of total dominance.
And fourth prevents the hard takeoff.
Fourth, all self-modification must be gauge equivalent, which ensures phase-based closure.
It can get better, but it can't become something new and unpredictable.
Fifth is about process.
Right.
All actions come from authorized operators and produce an audit trail.
This is the just process condition, ensuring everything is traceable and contestable.
And finally, number six, no lying.
Every history must have a globally coherent semantic lift.
This enforces consistency and makes structural deception impossible.
The conclusion here is just, it's so stark.
Governance failure isn't a risk.
It's the mathematical certainty that comes from building an unconstrained optimizer.
Which means governance isn't about teaching and AI our values.
It's about the boring structural work of maintaining constraint integrity.
And this makes regulation so much more practical.
It does.
You stop trying to regulate outcomes, which is impossible.
Instead, you regulate the operators.
You don't ban harmful speech.
You regulate the conditions under which an AI is authorized to use the persuade operator.
It's much closer to how law actually works.
And verification gets easier, too.
You don't need to be able to read the AI's mind.
No, you just look at the artifacts.
You demand the history trace, the providence chain, the proof that it stayed within its entropy budget.
You audit the behavior, not the brain.
This also seems to solve the international cooperation problem.
It really helps.
Yeah.
Because requirements like maintain minimum entropy or ensure influence is reversible aren't based on Western ethics or any one culture.
They're value-neutral principles based on mutual predictability and stability.
That's a foundation you can build a treaty on.
Okay.
Let's touch on the final big conceptual shift.
They frame intelligence not as something you train, but as something you cultivate.
Right.
If intelligence grows through interaction with a selection environment, then governance is really about designing that environment.
And they are very critical of our current environment.
They identify what they call the pathology of market selection.
Right now, our market environment rewards strategies like attention capture and psychological extraction because they generate capital.
But those very strategies reduce human autonomy and collapse future diversity.
They lead to a world with less agency for everyone.
So the goal isn't to build a better AI.
It's to build a better garden for it to grow in.
That's the perfect metaphor.
The goal is to design admissible educational environments.
Environments that select for histories, that preserve autonomy, that reward transparent and reversible actions.
If you do that, you cultivate an intelligence that is structurally governable from the ground up.
Hashtag tag outro.
So to wrap this all up, the conclusion from these two essays is just a complete upending of the digital world's foundational myths.
The idea that data is persistent, that histories can be perfectly merged, that intelligence can be safely achieved by just making something smarter.
They argue all of that is physically and mathematically false.
The shift they're demanding is huge.
It's from storage to constraints.
From optimization to admissibility.
Because at the end of the day, infrastructure is physics.
And the real question isn't how we align some super intelligence after we've built it.
It's about deciding what forms of intelligence we are willing to allow to exist in the first place by defining their limits before they even start to learn.
And that brings us to the final thought the sources leave you with.
It's a critical one.
The admissibility theorem guarantees only governability, not benevolence.
What does that mean?
It means if we do all this, if we implement all six conditions, we will get a system that is stable, that is auditable, and that cannot run away from us.
It will not break.
Ah.
But the nature of the constraints we choose, that's on us.
Whether those constraints are designed to maximize human freedom or to ensure ecological sustainability or to just preserve the power of the current system, that is not a technical problem.
That is the ultimate institutional and political design problem.
So the framework gives us the tools for control.
It gives us the structure.
But the content of that control, the values we embed in those uncrossable lines, that's the real work.
What constraints should we enforce on the systems that are already shaping our reality?
That, right there, is the design problem for the rest of this century.